League of Women Shoppers Records, 1937-2001
Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College
League of Women Shoppers Records
1937 - 2001
1937-1944
League of Women Shoppers
MS 328
1 box (.25 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
Consumer advocacy organization and labor reform advocacy organization. The purposes of the League of Women Shoppers were threefold: to investigate the working conditions in stores and factories; to organize consumers to support union organizing; and to protect and improve American living standards through grassroots. A few members represented include Alice Lesser Shepard, Lucille Montgomery, and Jessie Lloyd O'Connor. Materials include constitution and by-laws, correspondence, congressional committee hearing reports, news bulletins, and assorted publications.
Historical Note
Twenty socially conscious women who wished to use their power as consumers to obtain justice for workers founded the League of Women Shoppers (LWS) in New York City in June 1935. By 1937, the New York group claimed thousands of members and established branches in Boston, Chicago, Los Angeles, Philadelphia, Washington, D.C., Newark, New Jersey, and Columbus, Ohio. Although the LWS was officially non-partisan and, according to its constitution, "non-political," many members, including Jessie Lloyd O'Connor, Lillian Hellman, and Freda Kirchwey, had ties to other progressive and labor organizations. The official purposes of the League were threefold: to investigate the working conditions in the stores they patronized and the factories that produced the goods they consumed; to educate and organize consumers to support union organizing and to press for better wages and working conditions for workers who produced goods and provided services; and to protect and improve American living standards through both grassroots actions, such as boycotts and buyers' cooperatives, and legal regulation, such as rent and price controls and the protection of wages. In keeping with its unofficial progressive bent and political agenda, the LWS also supported other social justice causes, including civil rights for African-Americans and equal pay for women workers.
The Dies Committee branded the League of Women Shoppers a subversive organization in 1939. Nevertheless, League members continued to participate in a variety of consumer and union organizing campaigns through the early years of the 1940s. When the U.S. became formally involved in World War II, the League expanded its program to include efforts to support rationing and discourage black market sales of goods in short supply. In 1944, League members-whose numbers had decreased significantly from the late 1930s-worked for Franklin Roosevelt's reelection to a fourth term, but by 1945 the LWS engaged in fewer and fewer activities and soon faded out of existence.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The League of Women Shoppers Records consist of .25 linear feet dating from 1937-2001. These materials are far from a complete archive of the organization, but rather a selection of materials collected by one member. The bulk of the records date from 1937 through 1945 and focus on the national office of the League and its Chicago branch, though there are also a few records from Columbus, Ohio, Washington, D.C., and Newark, New Jersey. The documents reveal the history of the League of Women Shoppers, its goals, and the activities it conducted to promote them. Types of materials include agendas, correspondence, minutes, notes, printed material, and testimony.
Consumer education, union organizing, workplace conditions, and popular front activism are some of the major subjects addressed in the collection. The records offer insight into the goals and activities of a typical popular front-era progressive group that organized women on the basis of their roles as wives, mothers, and consumers and aimed to improve conditions for women and for the working-class as a whole. In addition to documenting the League of Women Shoppers itself, the papers document major twentieth century historical trends such as the achievements of the industrial union movement in the 1930s, and the increasing attention devoted to race and gender issues in U.S. politics during and after World War II.
Organization of the Collection
This collection is organized into two series:
I. Administration
II. Activities and Members
Information on Use
Terms of Access and Use
The collection is open for research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection.
History of the Collection
The League of Women Shoppers Records were donated to the Sophia Smith Collection in 1945 by Jessie Lloyd O'Connor, who had been active in the Chicago branch of the League.
Search Terms
O'Connor, Jessie Lloyd, 1904-; League of Women Shoppers--History--Sources; Consumer education--United States--History--Sources; Consumers' leagues--United States--History--Sources; Labor movement--History--20th century--Sources; Labor unions--United States--History--20th century--Sources; Popular fronts--United States--History--20th century; Work environment--United States--History--20th century--Sources
Additional Information
Related Material
Additional League of Women Shoppers material and other related papers can be found in the Jessie Lloyd O'Connor Papers in the Sophia Smith Collection, and in the vertical files of the Tamiment Library at New York University.
- SERIES I. ADMINISTRATION (1938-44), .1 linear ft.
  This series provides an overview of the League of Women Shoppers' national office and the affiliate organizations in Chicago, Illinois, Columbus, Ohio, Newark, New Jersey, and Washington, D.C. It is arranged in four subseries: Constitution and by-laws, National Board, National Executive Committee, Membership Committee meetings, and Local affiliates. The National Board material dates from 1938 through1944 and includes agendas, minutes, correspondence, and memoranda. Similarly, the material from the Local affiliates dates from 1938 through 1944 and includes agendas, minutes, and correspondence.
- SERIES II. ACTIVITIES AND MEMBERS (1937-2001), .15 linear ft.
  This series contains material that documents the activities undertaken by the League of Women Shoppers at the national and local levels between 1937 and 1944, and biographical material about two members of local League branches. It is organized into four subseries: Publicity, Testimony, Members, and Miscellaneous. Publicity, the largest subseries, dates from 1938 to 1945 and consists of leaflets, newsletters, pamphlets, notes, lists, and miscellaneous printed material, organized chronologically. Members includes biographical material about Alice Lesser Shepard, a member of the Eastchester, New York branch, and Lucille Montgomery, a progressive philanthropist, who was a key figure in the Washington, D.C. branch of the LWS.
- SERIES I. ADMINISTRATION (1938-44)
  - Constitution and by-laws: agenda, drafts, and finished documents, 1939, 1930s (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - National Board
    - Agendas, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Minutes, 1938-43, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence and memoranda, 1938-44 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - National Executive Committee: minutes, 1938-42 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - National Membership meetings: minutes, 1943-44 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Local affiliates
    - Agenda, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Minutes, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence, 1938-44 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- SERIES II. ACTIVITIES AND MEMBERS (1937-2001)
  - Publicity
    - Leaflets, 1938-45, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Newsletters, 1938-43, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Pamphlets: drafts and printed material, 1937-44 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Miscellaneous: lists, notes, and printed material, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Testimony, 1944, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Members: biographical notes and list, cir ca 1940, 20 00-01 (Box 1, Folder 15)